这篇文章将讨论不同的规格
This reading will look at different specs
对于类似的方法行为。
for similar method behaviors.
我们来谈谈权衡
And we'll talk about the trade-offs
在不同的规格之间。
between those different specs.
特别是，我们要看看
Particularly, we're going to look
在三维空间，三个标准
at three dimensions, three criteria we
可用于比较规格。
can use to compare specs.
首先，规范有多确定。
First, how deterministic the spec is.
从这个意义上说，它是否定义了
In the sense that, does it define
每个输入只有一个可能的输出？
only a single possible output for every input?
或者它允许实现的自由
Or does it allow the implemented freedom
为任何给定的输入从一组合法输出中选择？
to choose from a set of legal outputs for any given input?
第二，是陈述性的。
Second, is declarative it is.
它讨论输出应该是什么还是做什么
Does it talk about what the output should be or does
它明确指出了应该如何计算输出？
it say explicitly how the output should be computed?
这也影响了实施者的自由。
That also affects the implementers freedom.
第三，它有多强大。
And third, how strong it is.
规范是否有一套合法的实现
So does the spec have a set of legal implementations
那能满足吗？
that can satisfy it?
那套是小的还是大的？
And is that the set small or is it large?
现在，并不是所有的规格我们可以为一个模块选择
Now, not all specs we might choose for a module
同样有用。
are equally useful.
在本书中，我们将探讨
In this reading, we'll explore what
使一些规范比其他规范更好。
makes some of the specifications better than others.
我们先来谈谈决定论。
Let's start by talking about determinism.
所以请记住两个示例实现
So remember the two example implementations
我们在之前的阅读中发现的。
of find that we had in an earlier reading.
我们有一个，我们现在叫“先找到”。
We had this one that we're now calling find first.
从数组开始搜索
That searches from the beginning of the array
找到元素后立即返回。
and returns as soon as it finds the element.
然后，我们有了另一个实现
And then, we had this other implementation
我们现在要打电话给find last。
that we're now going to call find last.
从数组的末尾开始向后。
That starts at the end of the array and goes backwards.
所以它返回最后一次
So it returns the last occurrence
最后一次出现的索引。
of that value, the index of the last occurrence.
所以这些下标是第一个也是最后一个
So these subscripts first and last
不是真正的Java语法。
are not actual Java syntax.
我们只是用它们来区分
We're just using them here to distinguish
这两个实现是为了讨论。
the two implementations for the sake of discussion.
在实际的代码中，这个方法将被称为Find。
In the actual code, this method would just be called Find.
你要么要这个要么要那个
And you'd either have this one or that one
作为你的实现。
as your implementation.
现在，这里有一个可能的发现规范。
Now, here's one possible spec for Find.
我们称之为“找到一个”。
We're going to call it find exactly one.
这是先决条件。
And it's preconditioned.
上面写着你正在寻找的价值
It says that the value you are looking for
必须在数组中恰好出现一次。
must occur exactly once in the array.
它的后置条件是它将返回索引
And its post-condition says it's going to return the index where
出现该值。
that value occurs.
现在，这个规范是确定的。
Now, this spec is deterministic.
对于每一个满足这一前提的国家，
For every state that satisfies this precondition,
结果是完全确定的。
the outcome is completely determined.
数组中只有一个值出现，
There's only one occurrence of the value in the array,
所以只有一个索引值可能
so there's only one index where that value could possibly
发生。
occur.
而且没有有效的输入。
And there are no valid inputs.
没有满足以下条件的输入
No inputs that satisfy this precondition for which the find
只有一个方法会返回
exactly one method is going to return
多个有效输出。
more than one valid output.
这是确定性的。
It's deterministic.
现在，find first和find last都满足这个规范。
Now, both find first and find last satisfy this spec.
如果这是客户所依赖的规范
So if this is a specification in which the clients are relying
当他们调用find时，这两个实现
when they call find, then these two implementations
是等价的和可替代的。
are equivalent and substitutable for one another.
我们可以用任何一个作为实现
We could use either one as the implementation
这个发现方法。
of this Find method.
现在，这里有一个稍微不同的规范。
Now, here's a slightly different specification.
我们称之为在任何索引中查找一个或多个。
We're going to call it find one or more at any index.
以及它的后状态，而不是说
And its post-condition, instead of saying
这个值只出现一次
the value occurs exactly once, it just
表示值至少出现一次。
says the value occurs at least once.
它必须出现在数组中，但我们没有
It has to occur in the array, but we're not
只说一次。
saying it's exactly once.
后情况仍然显示
And the post-condition still says
我们要返回一些索引，我，
that we're going to return some index, i,
这个值出现的地方。
where that value occurs.
这个规格是不确定的。
This spec is not deterministic.
有一些输入。
There are some inputs.
当元音出现不止一次时
When the vowel occurs more than once
在数组中，实现可以选择
in the array, for which the implementation has a choice
关于返回哪个索引。
about which index to return.
该规范允许同一输入有多个有效输出。
This spec allows multiple valid outputs for the same input.
现在，我们说它不是确定性的。
Now, we say that it's not deterministic.
但我们要避免说不确定性。
But we're going to avoid saying non-deterministic.
因为在计算机中这个词的通常意义
Because the usual sense of that word in computer
科学意味着代码有时以一种方式运行
science means that the code sometimes behaves in one way
有时在另一个——即使是
and sometimes in another-- even if it's
在具有相同输入的同一程序中调用。
called in the same program with the same inputs.
当代码的行为依赖于
And this can happen when the code's behavior depends
在一个随机数上
on a random number that is generating
或者取决于同时预言的时间。
or when it depends on timing of concurrent prophecies.
但是一个不确定的规范
But a spec which is not deterministic
不必有不确定性
doesn't have to have a non-deterministic
实施。
implementation.
它可以通过完全确定的实现来满足。
It can be satisfied by a fully deterministic implementation.
换句话说，一个实现
In other words, an implementation that
总是会做出同样的选择
will always make the same choice when
你给它一个特殊的输入。
you give it a particular input.
但客户不能说——不能指望。
But the client can't tell-- can't bank on that.
所以我们要避免这种混乱
So we're going to avoid this confusion
用不确定这个词
with the word non-deterministic by saying
不确定的规格
that specs that are not deterministic
决心不足。
are underdetermined.
现在，这个不确定的发现规范，
Now, this underdetermined find spec,
找到一个或多个任何索引，再次，满足于
find one or more any index, is again, satisfied by both
先找后找。
find first and find last.
每个人都解决了不确定性
Each one resolves that underdeterminedness
以它自己完全确定的方式。
in its own fully deterministic way.
但问题是，find一个或多个任意索引的客户端
But the point is that a client of find one or more any index
不能依赖哪个实现
can't rely on which implementation
他们真的得到了。
they're actually getting.
它不能依赖于我的索引
It can't rely on which index i they will actually get
如果Val出现不止一次。
if Val appears more than once.
也许是第一个。
Maybe the first one.
也许是最后一个。
Maybe the last one.
也许中间有一个。
Maybe one in the middle.
现在，规格也可以满足了
Now, the spec could also be satisfied
通过不确定的实现。
by a nondeterministic implementation.
掷硬币决定的人
One that say tosses the coin to decide
是否开始搜索开头
whether to start searching the beginning
或者数组的末尾。
or the end of the array.
但在几乎所有的情况下，我们都会遇到它。
But in almost all cases, we're going to encounter it.
这个不确定的[听不见的]事实上
This underdetermined [INAUDIBLE] is actually
实现者在实现时所做的选择
a choice that's made by the implementer at implementation
时间。
time.
所以一个不确定的规格通常是
So an underdetermined spec is typically
由完全确定的实现来实现。
implemented by a fully deterministic implementation.